<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Viash</title>
<link>https://viash.io/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://viash.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://viash.io/viash.png</url>
<title>Viash</title>
<link>https://viash.io/blog/</link>
<height>38</height>
<width>144</width>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.6.42</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.8.7</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.7/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>The upcoming release of Nextflow introduces a new class for loading scripts and renamed the old class. This release supports this change by using reflection to detect the available class.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>viash build</code>: Fix error handling of non-generic errors in the build process or while pushing docker containers (PR #696).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowRunner</code>: ScriptParser was renamed to ScriptLoaderV1 in Nextflow 25.02.0-edge (PR #817). Backport from Viash 0.9.3 (PR #812). This fix uses reflection to detect whether ScriptParser exists – if not the ScriptLoaderFactory is used instead.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowRunner</code>: Backport path handling for <code>meta.resources_dir</code> for when symlinks are used (PR #817).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.7/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.9.3</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.9.3/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>The upcoming release of Nextflow introduces a new class for loading scripts and renamed the old class. This release supports this change by using reflection to detect the available class.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowRunner</code>: ScriptParser was renamed to ScriptLoaderV1 in Nextflow 25.02.0-edge (PR #812). This fix uses reflection to detect whether ScriptParser exists – if not the ScriptLoaderFactory is used instead.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowRunner</code>: Make sure scripts are generated with the right extension (PR #815).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.9.3/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.9.2</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.9.2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>This release fixes an edge case where output arguments for subworkflows were malformed.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li>CI: Added a CI for creating a release (PR #805).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>NextflowRunner</code>: Fix issue where output arguments for subworkflows were being returned as nested arrays instead of simple arrays (PR #798, PR #800).</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.9.2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.9.1</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.9.1/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Workflows can now publish results asynchronously by emitting multiple output channels. These results will then be merged into a published output behind the screens. Dependencies will use the new dedicated git url instead of the top level domain name.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="new-features" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-features">NEW FEATURES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>Nextflow</code> runner: allow emitting multiple output channels (PR #736).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Scope</code>: Add a <code>scope</code> field to the config (PR #782). This allows tuning how the components is built for release.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>viash-hub</code>: Change the url for viash-hub Git access to packages.viash-hub.com (PR #774).</p></li>
<li><p><code>RRequirements</code>: Allow single quotes to be used again in the <code>.script</code> field (PR #771).</p></li>
<li><p><code>scala</code>: Update Scala to Scala 3 (PR #759). For most of the code, this was a minor update, so no breaking changes are expected. The biggest change is how the exporting of the schema is done, but this has no impact on the user. However, switching to Scala 3 allows for additional features and improvements in the future.</p></li>
<li><p><code>--help</code>: Component <code>--help</code> messages will now display what built in <code>---</code> options are available (PR #784).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>config build</code>: Fix a bug where a missing main script would cause a stack trace instead of a proper error message (PR #776). The error message showed the path of the missing resource but it was easy to miss given the stack trace, besides it shouldn’t have been a stack trace anyway.</p></li>
<li><p><code>RRequirements</code>: Treat warnings as errors when installing R dependencies in Docker engines (PR #771).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Nextflow</code> runner: fix false-positive error when output argument arguments <code>required: true</code> are incorrectly flagged as missing input arguments (PR #778).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.9.1/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.9.0</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.9.0/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>This release restructures the introduces changes to the Viash config: - The <code>platforms</code> field is split into <code>runners</code> and <code>engines</code> - The <code>.functionality</code> layer has been removed from the config and all fields have been moved to the top layer</p>
<p>Changes are made to sanitize the built config output and include additional relevant meta data. The default <code>multiple_sep</code> has been changed from <code>:</code> to <code>;</code> to avoid conflicts with paths like <code>s3://foo/bar</code>.</p>
<p>Implemented a proper way of caching dependency repositories. The cache is stored under <code>~/.viash/repositories</code>.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="breaking-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="breaking-changes">BREAKING CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>runners</code> and <code>engines</code>: The usage of <code>platforms</code> is deprecated and instead these are split into <code>runners</code> and <code>engines</code> (PR #510). The <code>platforms</code> field is still supported but will be removed in a future release. In brief, the <code>native platform</code> became a <code>native engine</code> and <code>docker platform</code> became a <code>docker engine</code>. Additionally, the <code>native platform</code> and <code>docker platform</code> became a <code>executable runner</code>, <code>nextflow platform</code> became a <code>nextflow runner</code>. The fields of <code>docker platform</code> is split between <code>docker engine</code> and <code>docker runner</code>: <code>port</code>, <code>workdir</code>, <code>setup_strategy</code>, and <code>run_args</code> (set to <code>docker_run_args</code>) are captured by the <code>runner</code> as they define how the component is run. The other fields are captured by the <code>engine</code> as they define the environment in which the component is run. One exception is <code>chown</code> which is rarely set to false and is now always enabled.</p></li>
<li><p><code>arguments</code>: Merge arguments into argument_groups during a json decode prepare step (PR #574). The <code>--parse_argument_groups</code> option from <code>ns list</code> and <code>config view</code> is deprecated as it is now always enabled.</p></li>
<li><p><code>arguments</code>: Change default <code>multiple_sep</code> from <code>:</code> to <code>;</code> to avoid conflicts with paths like <code>s3://foo/bar</code> (PR #645). The previous behaviour of using <code>multiple_sep: ":"</code> can be achieved by adding a config mod to the <code>_viash.yaml</code>:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">config_mods</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">: </span><span class="ch" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">|</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2">  .functionality.argument_groups[true].arguments[.multiple == true].multiple_sep := ":"</span></code></pre></div></li>
<li><p><code>functionality</code>: Remove the <code>functionality</code> layer from the config and move all fields to the top layer (PR #649).</p></li>
<li><p><code>computational requirements</code>: Use 1000-base units instead of 1024-base units for memory (PR #686). Additionally, the memory units <code>kib</code>, <code>mib</code>, <code>gib</code>, <code>tib</code>, and <code>pib</code> are added to support 1024-base definitions.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowEngine</code>: Swap the order of execution of <code>runIf</code> and <code>filter</code> when calling <code>.run()</code>. This means that <code>runIf</code> is now executed before <code>filter</code> (PR #660).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="new-functionality" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-functionality">NEW FUNCTIONALITY</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>export json_schema</code>: Add a <code>--strict</code> option to output a subset of the schema representing the internal structure of the Viash config (PR #564).</p></li>
<li><p><code>config view</code> and <code>ns list</code>: Do not output internal functionality fields (#564). Additionally, add a validation that no internal fields are present when reading a Viash config file.</p></li>
<li><p><code>project config</code>: Add fields in the project config to specify default values for component config fields (PR #612). This allows for a more DRY approach to defining the same values for multiple components.</p></li>
<li><p><code>dependencies</code>: GitHub and ViashHub repositories now get properly cached (PR #699). The cache is stored in the <code>~/.viash/repositories</code> directory using sparse-checkout to only fetch the necessary files. During a build, the cache is checked for the repository and if it is found and still up-to-date, the repository is not cloned again and instead the cache is copied to a temporary folder where the files are checked out from the sparse-checkout.</p></li>
<li><p><code>ExecutableRunner</code>: Add a <code>---docker_image_id</code> flag to view the Docker image ID of a built executable (PR #741).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash ns query</code>: Add a query filter that allows selecting a single component by its path in a namespace environment (PR #744).</p></li>
<li><p><code>config schema</code>: Add <code>label</code> &amp; <code>summary</code> fields for Config, PackageConfig, argument groups, and all argument types (PR #743).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowEngine</code>: Added <code>runIf</code> functionality to <code>runEach</code> (PR #660).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>testbenches</code>: Add testbenches for local dependencies (PR #565).</p></li>
<li><p><code>testbenches</code>: Refactor testbenches helper functions to uniformize them (PR #565).</p></li>
<li><p><code>logging</code>: Preserve log order of StdOut and StdErr messages during reading configs in namespaces (PR #571).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Java 21 support</code>: Update Scala to 2.13.12 and update dependencies (PR #602).</p></li>
<li><p><code>project config</code>: Output the project config under the default name <code>ProjectConfig</code> instead of <code>Project</code> during schema export (PR #631). This is now important as the project config is now part of the component config. Previously this was overridden as the class name was <code>ViashProject</code> which was less descriptive.</p></li>
<li><p><code>package config</code>: Renamed <code>project config</code> to <code>package config</code> (PR #636). Now that we start using the config more, we came to the conclusion that “package” was better suited than “project”.</p></li>
<li><p><code>ns exec</code>: Added an extra field <code>{name}</code> to replace <code>{functionality-name}</code> (PR #649). No immediate removal of the old field is planned, but it is deprecated.</p></li>
<li><p><code>BashWrapper</code>: Added meta-data field <code>meta_name</code> as a replacement for <code>meta_functionality_name</code> (PR #649). No immediate removal of the old field is planned, but it is deprecated.</p></li>
<li><p><code>error message</code>: Improve the error message when using an invalid field in the config (#PR #662). The error message now includes the field names that are not valid if that happens to be the case or otherwise a more general error message.</p></li>
<li><p><code>config mods</code>: Improve the displayed error message when a config mod could not be applied because of an invalid path (PR #672).</p></li>
<li><p><code>docker_engine</code>: Deprecate <code>registry</code>, <code>organization</code> and <code>tag</code> fields in the <code>docker_engine</code> (PR #712). Currently these are hardly ever used and instead the <code>image</code> field is used to specify the full image name.</p></li>
<li><p><code>docker_engine</code>: Add <code>target_package</code> field to the <code>docker_engine</code> (PR #712). This field, together with the <code>target_organization</code> is used to specify the full built container image name. The fields use proper fallback for the values set in the component config and package config.</p></li>
<li><p><code>organization</code>: Remove the <code>organization</code> field from the component config (PR #712). The value is now directly used by the <code>docker_engine</code> as a fallback from the <code>target_organization</code> field.</p></li>
<li><p><code>ExecutableRunner</code>: Add parameter <code>docker_automount_prefix</code> to allow for a custom prefix for automounted folders (PR #739).</p></li>
<li><p><code>ExecutableRunner</code>: Make Docker runtime arguments configurable via the <code>---docker_run_args</code> argument (PR #740).</p></li>
<li><p><code>export json_schema</code>: Add <code>arguments</code> field to the <code>Config</code> schema (PR #755). Only for the non-strict version, the strict version of the viash config has these values merged into <code>argument_groups</code>.</p></li>
<li><p><code>scala</code>: Update Scala to 2.13.14 (PR #764).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowEngine</code>: Also parse <code>${id}</code> and <code>${key}</code> aside from <code>$id</code> and <code>$key</code> as identifier placeholders for filenames (PR #756).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>__merge__</code>: Handle invalid yaml during merging (PR #570). There was not enough error handling during this operation. Switched to the more advanced <code>Convert.textToJson</code> helper method.</p></li>
<li><p><code>config</code>: Anonymize paths in the config when outputting the config (PR #625).</p></li>
<li><p><code>schema</code>: Don’t require undocumented fields to set default values and add the <code>links</code> and <code>reference</code> fields to functionality as they were not meant only to be in the project config (PR #636).</p></li>
<li><p><code>export json_schema</code>: Fix minor inconsistencies and make the strict schema stricter by adapting to what Viash will effectively return (PR #666).</p></li>
<li><p><code>deprecation &amp; removal warning</code>: Improve the displayed warning where a deprecated or removed field could display a double ‘.’ when it field was located at the root level (PR #671).</p></li>
<li><p><code>resource path</code>: Don’t finalize the <code>path</code> field of a resource until it’s written as part of building a component (PR #668).</p></li>
<li><p><code>requirements</code>: Improve the error message when a Python or R requirement uses a single quote in the <code>.script</code> field (PR #675).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash test</code>: Fix Docker id between build and test components not being consistent when using a custom Docker registry (PR #679).</p></li>
<li><p><code>MainNSBuildNativeSuite</code>: Capture the error message when reading the configs so we can capture the expected warning message (PR #688). While almost all tests were already cleanly capturing their expected warning/error messages, this one was still remaining, resulting in warnings being shown in the output.</p></li>
<li><p><code>runners &amp; engines</code>: When applying a filter on empty runners or engines, the fallback default <code>native engine</code> and <code>executable runner</code> respectively are set before applying the filter (PR #691).</p></li>
<li><p><code>dependencies</code>: Fix resolving of dependencies of dependencies (PR #701). The stricter build config was now lacking the necessary information to resolve dependencies of dependencies. We added it back as <code>.build_info.dependencies</code> in a more structured, anonymized way.</p></li>
<li><p><code>dependencies</code>: Fix the <code>name</code> field of repositories possibly being outputted in the build config (PR #703).</p></li>
<li><p><code>symlinks</code>: Allow following of symlinks when finding configs (PR #704). This improves symlink functionality for <code>viash ns ...</code> and dependency resolving.</p></li>
<li><p><code>build_info</code>: Correctly set the <code>.build_info.executable</code> to <code>main.nf</code> when building a component with a Nextflow runner (PR #720).</p></li>
<li><p><code>vsh organization</code>: ViashHub repositories now use <code>vsh</code> as the default organization (PR #718). Instead of having to specify <code>repo: vsh/repo_name</code>, you can now just specify <code>repo: repo_name</code>, which is now also the prefered way.</p></li>
<li><p><code>testbenches</code>: Add a testbench to verify dependencies in dependencies from scratch (PR #721). The components are built from scratch and the dependencies are resolved from the local repositories.</p></li>
<li><p><code>docker_engine</code>: Fix a bug in how the namespace separator is handled (PR #722).</p></li>
<li><p><code>platforms</code>: Re-introduce the <code>--platform</code> and <code>--apply_platform</code> arguments to improve backwards compatibility (PR #725). When the argument is used, a deprecation warning message is printed on stderr. Cannot be used together with <code>--engine</code> or <code>--runner</code> and/or <code>--apply_engine</code> or <code>--apply_runner</code>.</p></li>
<li><p><code>nextflow_runner</code>: Fix refactoring error in the <code>findStates()</code> helper function (PR #733).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash ns exec</code>: Fix “relative fields” outputting absolute paths (PR# 737). Additionally, improve path resolution when using the <code>--src</code> argument.</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash ns</code>: Fix viash tripping over its toes when it encounters multiple failed configs (PR #761). A dummy config was used as a placeholder, but it always used the name <code>failed</code>, so duplicate config names were generated, which we check for nowadays.</p></li>
<li><p><code>bashwrapper</code>: Fix an issue where running <code>viash test</code> which builds the test docker container would ignore test failures but subsequential runs would work correctly (PR #754).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowEngine</code>: Fix escaping of odd filename containing special characters (PR #756). Filenames containing a <code>$</code> character caused Bash to try to interpret it as a variable.</p></li>
<li><p><code>json schema</code>: Fix repositories types with name incorrectly adding <code>withname</code> as type (PR #768).</p></li>
<li><p><code>json schema</code>: Change the ‘$schema’ field to ‘http://’ instead of ‘https://’ (PR #768). (Some?) Json validators use this value as a token and not as a URL.</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash test</code>: Fix an issue where the tests would not copy package config settings to determine the docker image name (PR #767).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.9.0/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.8.6</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.6/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Fix some issues in some edge cases. Add options for testing in a CI environment. Given that these options are not meant for general use, they are hidden from the help message. Some improvements are made to run in Nextflow Fusion.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="documentation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="documentation">DOCUMENTATION</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>docker setup strategy</code>: Fix inconsistencies in the documentation (PR #657).</p></li>
<li><p><code>repositories</code>: Fix <code>uri</code> -&gt; <code>repo</code> in the repositories documentation (PR #682).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="new-functionality" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-functionality">NEW FUNCTIONALITY</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>viash test</code> and <code>viash ns test</code>: Add a hidden <code>--dry_run</code> option to build the tests without executing them (PR #676).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash test</code> and <code>viash ns test</code>: Add a hidden <code>--deterministic_working directory</code> argument to use a fixed directory path (PR #683).</p></li>
<li><p><code>component names</code>: Verify that component namespace and name combinations are unique (PR #685).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Fix publishing state for output arguments with <code>multiple: true</code> (#638, PR #639).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Executable</code>: Check whether a multiple output file argument contains a wildcard (PR #639).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Fix a possible cause of concurrency issues (PR #669).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Resources</code>: Fix an issue where if the first resource is not a script, the resource is silently dropped (PR #670).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Docker automount</code>: Prevent adding a trailing slash to an automounted folder (PR #673).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Change the at-runtime generated nextflow process from an in-memory to an on-disk temporary file, which should cause less issues with Nextflow Fusion (PR #681).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.6/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.8.5</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.5/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Fix a bug when building a test docker container which requires a test resource. Additional improvements for the website documentation and support for the latest version of Nextflow are added.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Fix an issue with current nextflow-latest (24.01.0-edge) where our supporting library passes a GString instead of a String and results in a type mismatch (PR #640).</p></li>
<li><p><code>test resources</code>: Make non-script test resources available during building of a docker container for <code>viash test</code> (PR #652).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="documentation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="documentation">DOCUMENTATION</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>repositories</code>: Improve the repository documentation with links and a overview table with links (PR #643).</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.5/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.8.4</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.4/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Fix building components with dependencies that have symlinks in their paths.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>dependencies</code>: Fix dependencies with paths using symlinks (PR #621). The resolution for the <code>.build.vsh</code> was changed to use the <code>toRealPath</code> previously, so dependency resolution must take account possible resolved symlinks too.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.4/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.8.3</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.3/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Fix some edge cases and improve usability.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: properly resolve paths when a nextflow workflow has another nextflow workflow as dependency and the worktree contains a directory that is a symlink (PR #614).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Main</code>: Fixes a bug added by #294 which causes Viash to print a stacktrace instead of a helpful error message when <code>viash</code> is run without any arguments (#617, PR #618). Thanks <span class="citation" data-cites="mberacochea">@mberacochea</span> for pointing out this oversight!</p></li>
<li><p><code>Dependency</code>: When an alias is defined, pass the alias as a key to the <code>.run()</code> function (#601, PR #606).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.3/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.8.2</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>This release fixes a few bugs regarding dependencies and how the Nextflow platform handles Paths.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowTestHelper</code>: Do not hardcode a version of Nextflow in the testbench, but use the version of Nextflow that is installed on the system (PR #593).</p></li>
<li><p>GitHub Actions: Test different versions of Nextflow (22.04.5, latest, and latest-edge) (PR #593). Testing the latest Edge version of Nextflow will allow us to catch notice changes in Nextflow earlier.</p></li>
<li><p>Updates to the documentation and templates in the Git repo (#598, PR #600):</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Add contributing guidelines.</p></li>
<li><p>Add issue templates.</p></li>
<li><p>Reworked the pull request template.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>config</code>: Fix the main level of a component config not enforcing strict mode and instead allowing any field to be specified (PR #585).</p></li>
<li><p><code>dependencies</code>: Allow the user to define a local dependency with specifying <code>repository: local</code> as sugar syntax (PR #609). A local repository is the default value so it’s not required to be filled in, but allowing it with a sensible sugar syntax makes sense.</p></li>
<li><p><code>Repositories</code>: Fix a structural issue where a repository defined directly in a <code>dependency</code> would require the <code>name</code> field to be set (PR #607). Repository variants are created with and without the <code>name</code> field. Repositories under <code>.functionality.dependencies[]</code> use repositories without the <code>name</code> field, while repositories under <code>.functionality.repositories[]</code> use repositories with the <code>name</code> field.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Do not resolve remote paths relative to the –param_list file (PR #592).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Allow finding <code>.build.yaml</code> file when worktree contains a directory that is a symlink (PR #611).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.8.1</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.1/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>This release fixes a bug in the Nextflow platform where calling a workflow with the <code>.run()</code> function without specifying the <code>fromState</code> argument would result in an error when the input channel contained tuples with more than two elements.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Fix error when using <code>.run()</code> without using <code>fromState</code> and the input channel holds tuples with more than two elements (PR #587).</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.1/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.8.0</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.0/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Nextflow workflows definitions are picked up by Viash and assembled into a functional Nextflow workflow, reducing the amount of boilerplate code needed to be written by the user. It also adds a new <code>runIf</code> argument to the <code>NextflowPlatform</code> which allows for conditional execution of modules. We added new ‘dependencies’ functionality to allow for more advanced functionality to be offloaded and re-used in components and workflows.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="breaking-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="breaking-changes">BREAKING CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Changed the default value of <code>auto.simplifyOutput</code> from <code>true</code> to <code>false</code> (#522, PR #518). With <code>simplifyOutput</code> set to <code>true</code>, the resulting Map could be simplified into a <code>File</code> or a <code>List[File]</code> depending on the number of outputs. To replicate the previous behaviour, add the following config mod to <code>_viash.yaml</code>:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">config_mods</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">: </span><span class="ch" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">|</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2">  .platforms[.type == 'nextflow'].auto.simplifyOutput := true</span></code></pre></div></li>
<li><p><code>VDSL3Helper.nf</code>: Removed from the Viash jar file (PR #518). Its functions have been moved to <code>WorkflowHelper.nf</code>.</p></li>
<li><p><code>DataflowHelper.nf</code>: Added deprecation warning to functions from this file (PR #518).</p></li>
<li><p><code>preprocessInputs()</code> in <code>WorkflowHelper.nf</code>: Added deprecation warning to <code>preprocessInputs()</code> because this function causes a synchronisation event (PR #518).</p></li>
<li><p><code>author.props</code>: Removed deprecated <code>props</code> field (PR #536). Deprecated since 0.7.4.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="new-functionality" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-functionality">NEW FUNCTIONALITY</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>dependencies</code>: Add <code>dependencies</code> and <code>repositories</code> to <code>functionality</code> (PR #509). The new functionality allows specifying dependencies and where to retrieve (repositories) them in a component, and subsequentially allows advanced functionality to be offloaded and re-used in scripts and projects. This is alike e.g.&nbsp;<code>npm</code>, <code>pip</code> and many others. A big difference is that we aim to provide the needed boilerplate code to ease the usage of the dependencies in scripts, workflows and pipelines. Note that the dependency is required to be a built Viash component or project and not a random file or code project found externally. This is needed to provide the necessary background information to correctly link dependencies into a component.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowScript</code> &amp; <code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Merged code for merging the <code>main.nf</code> files for VDSL3 components and wrapped Nextflow workflows (PR #518). By aligning the codebase for these two, wrapped Nextflow workflows are more similar to VDSL3 components. For example, you can override the behaviour of a wrapped Nextflow workflow using the <code>.run()</code> method. Status of a workflows <code>.run()</code> arguments:</p>
<ul>
<li>Works as intended: <code>auto.simplifyInput</code>, <code>auto.simplifyOutput</code>, <code>fromState</code>, <code>toState</code>, <code>map</code>, <code>mapData</code>, <code>mapPassthrough</code>, <code>filter</code>, <code>auto.publish = "state"</code></li>
<li>Does not work (yet): <code>auto.transcript</code>, <code>auto.publish = true</code>, <code>directives</code>, <code>debug</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>In a next PR, each of the dependencies will have their values overridden by the arguments of the <code>.run</code>.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: The data passed to the input of a component and produced as output by the component are now validated against the arguments defined in the Viash config (PR #518).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Use <code>stageAs</code> to allow duplicate filenames to be used automatigically (PR #518).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: When wrapping Nextflow workflows, throw an error if the IDs of the output channel doesn’t match the IDs of the input channel (PR #518). If they don’t, the workflow should store the original ID of the input tuple in the in the <code>_meta.join_id</code> field inside the state as follows: Example input event: <code>["id", [input: file(...)]]</code>, Example output event: <code>["newid", [output: file(...), _meta: [join_id: "id"]]]</code></p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Added new <code>.run()</code> argument <code>runIf</code> - a function that determines whether the module should be run or not (PR #553). If the <code>runIf</code> closure evaluates to <code>true</code>, then the module will be run. Otherwise it will be passed through without running.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="major-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="major-changes">MAJOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>WorkflowHelper.nf</code>: The workflow helper was split into different helper files for each of the helper functions (PR #518). For now, these helper files are pasted together to recreate the <code>WorkflowHelper.nf</code>. In Viash development environments, don’t forget to run <code>./configure</code> to start using the updated Makefile.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Set default tag to <code>"$id"</code> (#521, PR #518).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Refactoring of helper functions (PR #557).</p>
<ul>
<li>Cleaned up <code>processConfig()</code>: Removed support for <code>functionality.inputs</code> and <code>functionality.outputs</code></li>
<li>Cleaned up <code>processConfig()</code>: Removed support for <code>.functionality.argument_groups[].argument</code> containing a list of argument ids as opposed to the arguments themselves.</li>
<li>Rewrote <code>--param_list</code> parser.</li>
<li>Removed unused function <code>applyConfig()</code> and <code>applyConfigToOneParamSet()</code>.</li>
<li>Refactored <code>channelFromParams()</code> to make use of new helper functions.</li>
<li>Removed deprecated <code>paramsToChannel()</code>, <code>paramsToList()</code>, <code>viashChannel()</code>.</li>
<li>Deprecated <code>preprocessInputs()</code> – use the wrapped Viash Nextflow functionality instead.</li>
<li>Refactored <code>preprocessInputs()</code> to make use of new helper functions.</li>
<li>Deprecated run arguments <code>map</code>, <code>mapData</code>, <code>mapPassthrough</code>, <code>renameKeys</code>.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Throw error when unexpected keys are passed to the <code>.run()</code> method (#512, PR #518).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Testbenches</code>: Add testbenches for the new <code>dependencies</code> functionality and other small coverage improvements (PR #524).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Use <code>moduleDir</code> instead of <code>projectDir</code> to determine the resource directory.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Rename internal VDSL3 variables to be more consistent with regular Viash component variables and avoid naming clashes (PR #553).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="documentation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="documentation">DOCUMENTATION</h3>
<ul>
<li>Minor fixes to VDSL3 reference documentation (PR #508).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>WorkflowHelper.nf</code>: Only set default values of output files which are <strong>not already set</strong>, and if the output file argument is <strong>not required</strong> (PR #514).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: When using <code>fromState</code> and <code>toState</code>, do not throw an error when the state or output is missing an optional argument (PR #515).</p></li>
<li><p><code>export cli_autocomplete</code>: Fix output script format and hide <code>--loglevel</code> and <code>--colorize</code> (PR #544). Masked arguments are usable but might not be very useful to always display in help messages.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.8.0/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.7.5</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.5/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>This release contains minor breaking change due to deprecated or outdated functionality being removed.</p>
<p>New functionality includes:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Export a JSON schema for the Viash config with <code>viash export json_schema</code></p></li>
<li><p>Export a Bash or Zsh autocomplete script with <code>viash export cli_autocomplete</code></p></li>
<li><p>Nextflow VDSL3 modules now have a <code>fromState</code> and <code>toState</code> argument to allow for better control of the data that gets passed to the module and how the state is managed in a Nextflow workflow.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="breaking-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="breaking-changes">BREAKING CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>viash export cli_schema</code>: Added <code>--format yaml/json</code> argument, default format is now a YAML (PR #448).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash export config_schema</code>: Added <code>--format yaml/json</code> argument, default format is now a YAML (PR #448).</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowLegacyPlatform</code>: Removed deprecated code (PR #469).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash_*</code>: Remove legacy viash_build, viash_test and viash_push components (PR #470).</p></li>
<li><p><code>ComputationalRequirements</code>, <code>Functionality</code>, <code>DockerPlatform</code>, <code>DockerRequirements</code>: Remove documentation of removed fields (PR #477).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="new-functionality" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-functionality">NEW FUNCTIONALITY</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>viash export json_schema</code>: Export a json schema derived from the class reflections and annotations already used by the <code>config_schema</code> (PR #446).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash export config_schema</code>: Output <code>default</code> values of member fields (PR #446).</p></li>
<li><p><code>CI</code>: Test support for different Java versions on GitHub Actions (PR #456). Focussing on LTS releases starting from 11, so this is 11 and 17. Also test latest Java version, currently 20.</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash test</code> and <code>viash ns test</code>: add <code>--setup</code> argument to determine the docker build strategy before a component is tested (PR #451).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash export cli_autocomplete</code>: Export a Bash or Zsh autocomplete script (PR #465 &amp; #482).</p></li>
<li><p><code>help message</code>: Print the relevant help message of (sub-)command when <code>--help</code> is given as an argument instead of only printing the help message when it is the leading argument and otherwise silently disregarding it (initially added in PR #472, replaced by PR #496). This is a new feature implemented in Scallop 5.0.0.</p></li>
<li><p><code>Logging</code>: Add a Logger helper class (PR #485 &amp; #490). Allows manually enabling or disabling colorizing TTY output by using <code>--colorize</code>. Add provisions for adding debugging or trace code which is not outputted by default. Changing logging level can be changed with <code>--loglevel</code>. These CLI arguments are currently hidden.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Nextflow VDSL3 modules now have a <code>fromState</code> and <code>toState</code> argument to allow for better control of the data that gets passed to the module and how the state is managed in a Nextflow workflow (#479, PR #501).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>PythonScript</code>: Pass <code>-B</code> to Python to avoid creating <code>*.pyc</code> and <code>*.pyo</code> files on importing helper functions (PR #442).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash config</code>: Special double values now support <code>+.inf</code>, <code>-.inf</code> or <code>.nan</code> values (PR #446 and PR #450). The stringified versions <code>"+.inf"</code>, <code>"-.inf"</code> or <code>".nan"</code> are supported as well. This is in line with the yaml spec.</p></li>
<li><p><code>system environment variables</code>: Add wrapper around <code>sys.env</code> and provide access to specific variables (PR #457). Has advantages for documentation output and testbenches.</p></li>
<li><p><code>testbench</code>: Added some minor testbenches to tackle missing coverage (PR #459, #486, #488, #489, #492 &amp; #494).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash export config_schema</code>: Simplify file structure (PR #464).</p></li>
<li><p><code>helpers.Format</code>: Add a helper for the Format helper object (PR #466).</p></li>
<li><p><code>testbench</code>: Use config deriver to create config variants for testing (PR #498). This reduces the amount of config files that need to be maintained.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>viash config</code>: Validate Viash config Yaml files better and try to give a more informative error message back to the user instead of a stack trace (PR #443).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash ns build</code>: Fix the error summary when a setup or push failure occurs. These conditions were not displayed and could cause confusion (PR #447).</p></li>
<li><p><code>testbench</code>: Fix the viash version switch test bench not working for newer Java versions (PR #452).</p></li>
<li><p><code>malformed input exception</code>: Capture MalformedInputExceptions when thrown by reading files with invalid Ascii characters when unsupported by Java (PR #458).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash project file parsing</code>: Give a more informative message when the viash project file fails to parse correctly (PR #475).</p></li>
<li><p><code>DockerPlatform</code>: Fix issue when mounting an input or output folder containing spaces (PR #484).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Config mod</code>: Fix a config mod where the filter should execute multiple deletes (PR #503).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="documentation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="documentation">DOCUMENTATION</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Add documentation for the usage and arguments of a VDSL3 module (PR #501).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="internal-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="internal-changes">INTERNAL CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowVDSL3Platform</code>: Renamed to <code>NextflowPlatform</code> (PR #469).</p></li>
<li><p>Rename mentions of <code>NextFlow</code> to <code>Nextflow</code> (PR #476).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Reference static pages</code>: Move <code>.qmd</code> files from the website to a local folder here; <code>docs/reference</code> (PR #504). This way we can track behaviour changes that need to be documented locally.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.5/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.7.4</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.4/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Some small fixes and consistency improvements. A few Quality of Life improvements were made e.g.&nbsp;to override the Docker <code>entrypoint</code> when working with Nextflow and providing default labels when building a Nextflow workflow.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="new-functionality" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-functionality">NEW FUNCTIONALITY</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Add default labels in Nextflow config files that set default values for cpu and memory settings (PR #412). Values are more or less logarithmically spaced (1, 2, 5, 10, …).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Author</code>: Added <code>info</code> field to authors. Deprecated <code>props</code> field (PR #423).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash config view</code> and <code>viash ns list</code>: Set the <code>.info.output</code> path when a platform argument is provided.</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash ns exec</code>: Added two more fields:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>{output}</code>: path to the destination directory when building the component</li>
<li><code>{abs-output}</code>: absolute path to the destination directory when building the component</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><code>DockerPlatform</code>: Add <code>entrypoint</code> and <code>cmd</code> parameters to the docker platform config that allows overriding the default docker container settings (PR #432).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>Nextflow VDSL3</code>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Add profiles to the Nextflow Config file when the main script is a <code>NextflowScript</code> (#408).</li>
<li>Add a <code>script</code> parameter in Nextflow Config file to add a single string or list of strings to the <code>nextflow.config</code> (PR #430).</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><code>Scripts</code>: Remove the <code>entrypoint</code> parameter for all script types except <code>NextflowScript</code> (#409). All these scripts had to check individually whether the parameter was unset, now it can be done in the <code>Script</code> apply method.</p></li>
<li><p><code>schema export</code>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Restructure Nextflow-Directives, -Auto and -Config into a <code>nextflowParameters</code> group (PR #412). Previously only NextflowDirectives was exposed.</li>
<li>Restructure the format to group authors &amp; computational requirements together with functionality (PR #426).</li>
<li>Restructure the Viash Config and Project Config pages under a <code>config</code> category (PR #426).</li>
<li>Add references in Functionality and Nextflow VDSL3 to the new documentation pages (PR #426).</li>
<li>Add description and/or examples for platforms and requirements (PR #428).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>viash config inject</code>: Fix an empty line being added at the script start for each time <code>viash config inject</code> was run (#377).</p></li>
<li><p><code>WorkflowHelper</code>: Fixed an issue where passing a remote file URI (for example <code>http://</code> or <code>s3://</code>) as <code>param_list</code> caused <code>No such file</code> errors.</p></li>
<li><p><code>BashWrapper</code>: Fix escaping of the included script where a line starting with a pipe character with optional leading spaces is stripped of the leading spaces and pipe character. This was quite unlikely to happen except when <code>viash config inject</code> was called on a Nextflow Script, which lead to no real config code being injected however workflows were getting corrupted. (#421)</p></li>
<li><p><code>Deprecation testbench</code>: Add missing classes to be checked (PR #426).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.4/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.7.3</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.3/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Fix minor issues in the documentation and with the way parent paths of resources are printed a config view.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>DockerPlatform</code>: Fixed example in documentation for the <code>namespace_separator</code> parameter (PR #396).</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash config view</code>: Resource parent paths should be directories and not file (PR #398).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.3/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.7.2</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>This update adds functionality to resolve paths starting with a slash as relative to the project directory, improves handling of info metadata in the config, and fixes to the operator precedence of config mods.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="new-functionality" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-functionality">NEW FUNCTIONALITY</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Resolve resource and merge paths starting with a slash (<code>/</code>) as relative to the project directory (PR #380). To define absolute paths (which is not recommended anyway), prefix the path with the <code>file://</code> protocol. Examples:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>/foo</code> is a file or directory called <code>foo</code> in the current project directory.</li>
<li><code>file:/foo</code> is a file or directory called <code>foo</code> in the system root.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>viash config view</code>: Do not modify (e.g.&nbsp;strip empty fields) of the <code>.functionality.info</code> and <code>.functionality.arguments[].info</code> fields (#386).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>ConfigMods</code>: Fix operator precedence issues with conditions in the config mod parsers (PR #390).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="internal-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="internal-changes">INTERNAL CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Clean up unused code (PR #380).</p></li>
<li><p>Move circe encoders/decoders for File and Path from <code>io.viash.functionality.arguments</code> to <code>io.viash.helpers.circe</code> (PR #380).</p></li>
<li><p>Store the project root directory (that is, the directory of the <code>_viash.yaml</code>) in a ViashProject object (PR #380).</p></li>
<li><p>Tests: Reworked language tests to be grouped in their own subfolder and split off the bash language test from the general <code>testbash</code> folder (PR #381).</p></li>
<li><p>Tests: Add additional language tests for <code>viash config inject</code> (PR #381).</p></li>
<li><p>Tests: Added test for <code>io.viash.helpers.IO</code> (PR #380).</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.7.1</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.1/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>This is a minor release which improves caching in VDSL3 components and changes the formats of the schema files for the Viash config and CLI.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>DataflowHelper</code>: Add assertions and <code>def</code>s.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>VDSL3</code>: Only the first two elements from an event in a channel are now passed to a process. This avoids calculating cache entries based on arguments that are not used by the process, causing false-negative cache misses.</p></li>
<li><p><code>config_schema</code>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Correct some incorrect markdown tags.</li>
<li>Add project config.</li>
<li>Correct documentation/markdown tags to the correct order.</li>
<li>Add summary description and example for ‘resource’ and ‘argument’, to be used on the reference website.</li>
<li>Add documentation for the Nextflow directives.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><code>cli_schema</code>: Correct documentation/markdown tags to the correct order.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.1/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.7.0</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.0/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Default namespace separator has been changed from <code>_</code> to <code>/</code>. This means Docker images will be named <code>&lt;Registry&gt;/&lt;Organization&gt;/&lt;Namespace&gt;/&lt;Name&gt;</code> by default. For example, <code>ghcr.io/openpipelines-bio/mapping/cellranger_count</code> instead of <code>ghcr.io/openpipelines-bio/mapping_cellranger_count</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>Removed deprecated code of unused functionality to simplify code.</p>
<ul>
<li>Shorthand notation for specitying input/output arguments</li>
<li>Shorthand notation for specifying Docker requirements</li>
<li>Legacy Nextflow platform</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Improvements in VDSL3 and the Nextflow Workflow Helper to make behaviour more predictable and fixing some bugs in the meantime. Run the following to get access to the updated helpers:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode bash code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">WF_DIR</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"src/wf_utils"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">[[</span> <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-d</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$WF_DIR</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">]]</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">||</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mkdir</span> <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-p</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$WF_DIR</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">viash</span> export resource platforms/nextflow/ProfilesHelper.config <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$WF_DIR</span>/ProfilesHelper.config</span>
<span id="cb1-4"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">viash</span> export resource platforms/nextflow/WorkflowHelper.nf <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$WF_DIR</span>/WorkflowHelper.nf</span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">viash</span> export resource platforms/nextflow/DataflowHelper.nf <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$WF_DIR</span>/DataflowHelper.nf</span></code></pre></div></li>
<li><p>Improvements to test benches and several bug fixes.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="breaking-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="breaking-changes">BREAKING CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Viash config: Previously deprecated fields are now removed.</p>
<ul>
<li><code>functionality.inputs</code>: Use <code>arguments</code> or <code>argument_groups</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>functionality.outputs</code>: Use <code>arguments</code> or <code>argument_groups</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>functionality.tests</code>: Use <code>test_resources</code> instead. No functional difference.</li>
<li><code>functionality.enabled</code>: Use <code>status: enabled</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>functionality.requirements.n_proc</code>: Use <code>cpus</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.DockerPlatform.privileged</code>: Add a <code>--privileged</code> flag in <code>run_args</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.DockerPlatform.apk</code>: Use <code>setup: [{ type: apk, packages: ... }]</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.DockerPlatform.apt</code>: Use <code>setup: [{ type: apt, packages: ... }]</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.DockerPlatform.yum</code>: Use <code>setup: [{ type: yum, packages: ... }]</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.DockerPlatform.r</code>: Use <code>setup: [{ type: r, packages: ... }]</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.DockerPlatform.python</code>: Use <code>setup: [{ type: python, packages: ... }]</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.DockerPlatform.docker</code>: Use <code>setup: [{ type: docker, run: ... }]</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.DockerPlatform.docker.setup.resources</code>: Use <code>setup: [{ type: docker, copy: ... }]</code> instead.</li>
<li><code>platforms.NextflowLegacy</code>: Use the Nextflow VDSL3 platform instead.</li>
<li><code>functionality.ArgumentGroups</code>: No longer supports strings referring to arguments in the <code>arguments:</code> section. Instead directly put the arguments inside the argument groups.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><code>viash_install</code>: The bootstrap script has been reworked in line with the project config introduced in 0.6.4:</p>
<ul>
<li>The default location for installing the Viash executable is now <code>./viash</code> (was: <code>bin/viash</code>).</li>
<li>The new <code>viash_install</code> support <code>--output</code> and <code>--tag</code>.</li>
<li>The various settings that existed in <code>viash_install</code> (organisation, tag, …) are moved to the project config.</li>
</ul>
<p>Please note that this new <code>viash_install</code> bootstrap script can be run from the CLI using:</p>
<pre><code>curl -fsSL dl.viash.io | bash</code></pre>
<p>The old <code>get.viash.io</code> is still available but points to the version 0.6.7 version of this component and is deprecated.</p></li>
<li><p><code>WorkflowHelper</code>: <code>paramsToList</code>, <code>paramsToChannel</code> and <code>viashChannel</code> are now deprecated and will be removed in a future release.</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash (ns) build</code>: Change the default value of the namespace separator in a Docker platform from <code>_</code> to <code>/</code>. Add <code>".platforms[.type == 'docker'].namespace_separator := '_'"</code> to the project config <code>_viash.yaml</code> to revert to the previous behaviour.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="major-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="major-changes">MAJOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>VDSL3</code>: now uses the newly implemented <code>channelFromParams</code> and <code>preprocessInputs</code> instead of <code>viashChannel</code>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="new-features" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-features">NEW FEATURES</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>WorkflowHelper</code>: Added <code>preprocessInputs</code> and <code>channelFromParams</code> to replace <code>paramsToList</code>, <code>paramsToChannel</code> and <code>viashChannel</code>. This refactor allows processing parameters that are already in a Channel using <code>preprocessInputs</code>, which is necessary when passing parameters from a workflow to a subworkflow in a Nextflow pipeline.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>Main</code>: Capture build, setup and push errors and output an exit code.</p></li>
<li><p><code>File downloading</code>: Add check to pre-emptively catch file errors (e.g.&nbsp;404).</p></li>
<li><p><code>Scala</code>: Updated to Scala 2.13 and updated several dependencies.</p></li>
<li><p><code>Main</code>: Improve <code>match</code> completeness in some edge cases and throw exceptions where needed.</p></li>
<li><p><code>Changelog</code>: Reformat the changelog to a more structured format. For every release, there is now a date, title, and summary. This both improves the changelog itself but can then also be used to postprocess the CHANGELOG programmatically.</p></li>
<li><p><code>VDSL3</code>: Add a default value for <code>id</code> when running a VDSL3 module as a standalone pipeline.</p></li>
<li><p><code>TestBenches</code>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Verify switching of Viash versions</li>
<li>Prepare ConfigDeriver by copying base resources to the targetFolder. Use cases so far showed that it’s always required and it simplifies the usage.</li>
<li>Remove some old &amp; unmaintained IntelliJ Idea <code>editor-fold</code> tags. Given that the testbenches were split up, these were broken but also no longer needed.</li>
<li>Add 2 testbenches for computational requirements when running <code>viash run</code> or <code>viash test</code>.</li>
<li>Added tests for different values for the <code>--id</code> and <code>--param_list</code> parameters of VDSL3 modules.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><code>viash test</code>: Use <code>test</code> as a random tag during testing, instead of <code>test</code> plus a random string.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>WorkflowHelper</code>: fixed where passing a relative path as <code>--param_list</code> would cause incorrect resolving of input files.</p></li>
<li><p><code>Testbenches</code>: Fix GitTest testbench to correctly increment temporary folder naming and dispose them after the test finishes.</p></li>
<li><p><code>viash xxx url</code>: Fix passing a url to viash as the config file to process. Add a short testbench to test principle functionality.</p></li>
<li><p><code>Testbenches</code>: Simplify <code>testr</code> container.</p></li>
<li><p><code>Main</code>: Improve error reporting to the user in some cases where files or folders can’t be found. Depending on the thrown exception, more or less context was given.</p></li>
<li><p><code>VDSL3</code>: Create parent directory of output files before starting the script.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.7.0/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.6.7</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.6.7/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>Another minor release which contains several quality of life improvements for the Nextflow VDSL3 platform, as well as automated warnings for deprecated functionality.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="minor-changes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minor-changes">MINOR CHANGES</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Create directories during a stub run when output path is a nested directory (PR #314).</p></li>
<li><p>Automatically generate a warning for deprecated parameters while parsing a .viash.yaml configuration file using the inline documentation deprecation annotations.</p></li>
<li><p>Add a “planned removal” field in the deprecation annotations.</p></li>
<li><p>Add testbenches to verify proper formatting of the deprecation versions and compare current version to the planned removal version so no deprecated parameters get to stick around beyond what was planned.</p></li>
<li><p><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Nextflow processes are created lazily; that is, only when running a Nextflow workflow (PR #321).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>NextflowPlatform</code>: Automatically split Viash config strings into strings of length 65000 since the JVM has a limit (65536) on the length of string constants (PR #323).</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.6.7/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Viash 0.6.6</title>
  <dc:creator>Viash Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.6.6/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="whats-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new">What’s new?</h2>
<p>This release fixes an issue where stderr was being redirected to stdout.</p>
</section>
<section id="full-changelog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-changelog">Full changelog</h2>
<section id="bug-fixes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bug-fixes">BUG FIXES</h3>
<ul>
<li>Don’t redirect stderr to stdout when switching Viash versions (#312).</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>New Release</category>
  <guid>https://viash.io/blog/posts/viash-0.6.6/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
